hi this is Anil and welcome to the video
tutorial for the learning lag on Cypress
plus programming so in this tutorial
we're going to learn how to overload the
class member access operator so this
class member access operator is one of
the special operators available in C++
you know it is nothing but the arrow
operator so this arrow operator is a
point operator and also called the class
member operator so this operator is
considered as a unary operator when
overloading so the general usage of this
arrow operator is you know we used to
have an object and then the arrow
operator and then the element so here
the object is the object that activates
the call so this object is going to call
the operator function for this arrow
operator that we write and also when you
overload this arrow operator or the
class member access operator the
operator function must return a pointer
to an object of the class where we
overload this arrow operator
so here the element must be some member
accessible within the object so now you
know we can see how to overload this
operator in our program so just for the
demonstration purpose I have already
created a class in this program and we
have a class called marks and we have a
member called mark and we have a public
constructor and which is going to take
one value and it's going to initialize
the member mark and also we have a
public method you know which is going to
print out the value store in this member
mark all right the next thing that we're
going to do is we can have overload the
arrow operator or we going to overload
the class member access operator so this
class member access operator is one of
the special operator available in C++
and that's why we cannot use friend
function to overload this operator and
also the operator function that we can
write must be a non-static member of
this class all right now here first we
need to specify the return type
and also I told you that you know the
operator function must return a pointer
to an object of the class where this
operator function is defined and that's
why it's going to be a pointer of this
class marks marks star and then the
keyword operator and then the operator
symbol which is this arrow operator and
then a pair of parentheses and between
that parenthesis no parameters that's
because you know this arrow operator or
this class member access operator is
considered as a unary operator and the
only operand is going to work on will be
implicitly passed by the C++ so here
inside this operator function we just
gonna return the this pointer so it's
going to be returned and this that's it
so now we have overloaded the arrow
operator or the class member access
operator next we're going to create an
object of this class marks and let's say
marks and Anil smoke the object name and
we can initialize that for example 65
now we can access this what's your mark
methyl since it is public you know this
mark is private by using the dot
operator and to do that we need to write
the object name that is Anil's mark and
then dot operator and then the method in
that is was your mark
alright so now we have overloaded this
error operator that's why we can use
this operator just like the way we were
using this dot operator so we can also
access this by using the arrow operator
so we don't have a pointer here and
first I'm going to run this and then I'm
going to expand it so build and run all
right now you guys can see we got a hey
I got 65 marks and hey I got 65 marks so
we have accessed this member metal was
your mark by using the dot operator and
arrow operator so here when we use this
arrow operator
you know this onion smoke is going to
call the operator function and this
object will be passed as a current
object to this operator function so the
this pointer is going to contain the
address of this object passed and that's
why you know this operator is gonna
return the pointer so here when we use
this dot operator we are referring that
through object because of this
overloaded arrow operator you know we
get the address here because of the
return statement of this this here so
that's why we can access that just like
the way we were using the the pointer
and the arrow operator so this is how
you guys can overload the arrow operator
or the class member axis operator in C++
so thank you for watching this dome for
to subscribe and like my facebook page
and and stay updated with the latest
videos that we're gonna make and I'll
see you know next tutorial